Finding Aid for Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science (University of Michigan) records, 1920-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science (University of Michigan) records
1920-1997
1970-1997
University of Michigan. Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science.
87151 Bimu C146 2
Electrical engineering was established as a department in the College of Engineering in 1895. In 1971 it was renamed as the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering. The Department of Computer and Communication Science was transferred from the College of Literature, Science and the Arts in 1984. The faculties and courses were merged under new designation Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science. Departmental records include administration material relating to policies and budget, annual reports and reviews, topical files, photographs, and personnel files of inactive faculty and research scientists. Records describe the facilities, curriculum, and teaching and research activities within the department.
10 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Records were received from the Department of Electrical Engineering beginning in 1971. Periodic Accessions are received (donor no. 6717 ).
The Department of Electrical Engineering records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The Department of Electrical Engineering record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 5-10
The University of Michigan Department of Electrical Engineering was founded as part of the College of Engineering in 1895/96 through the transfer of several courses originally offered by the Department of Physics. Electrical engineering proved a popular area of study. Throughout the first two decades of the twentieth century course offerings were increased and the size of the department’s faculty was expanded. In 1926, the number of faculty members within the department stabilized, but growth resumed during World War II. Subsequent post-war research into both electronics and computer technology spurred continuing growth within the department. In July, 1971 the department’s name was altered to reflect technological change, becoming the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering.
Research was always a part of the department’s activities, however, prior to World War I it was usually carried out on an individual basis. In 1920 the organization of the Department of Engineering Research by the College of Engineering facilitated a gradual shift towards group efforts, often funded by private industry. During World War II the federal government first began to broadly fund research and the department received and continues to receive a large number of federally sponsored research projects.
In July 1984 the Department of Computer and Communication Science in the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts transferred its faculty and merged with the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering. This combined department was renamed the Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science in the College of Engineering. Researchers can find more information about the department at its web site: http://www.eecs.umich.edu/eecs/
The Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science records contain correspondence, departmental review reports, committee minutes, faculty and student surveys, personnel records and photographs. The records span the years 1920-1997.
The records are arranged in seven series: Administrative Budget/ Financial, Department Review and Report, Histories, Topical, Photographs, and Personnel.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Electrical Engineering.; University of Michigan--Research.Research.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science.; Computer engineering.; Electric engineering--Study and teaching.; Engineers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Computers.; Engineering.; Laboratories.; Rockets.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Electrical and Computer Engineering.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Administrative, 1937-1987
  The Administrative (1937-1987) series is divided into two sub-series. The Correspondence sub-series contains letters and memos. The Committees sub-series contains memos, correspondence and minutes generated by administrative committees.
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence and Memos, 1937-1969 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Committees, 1976-1986
    - Administrative Committee
      - 1985-1986, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    - Chairman’s Advisory Committee
      - 1984-1985 (Box 1)
      - 1985-1986 (Box 1)
      - 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    - Computer Policy Committee
      - Report: “Hierarchical Computing at the University of Michigan,”, 1976 (Box 1)
      - Report: “Hierarchical Computing at the University of Michigan Pt. 2,”, 1977 (Box 1)
      - 1986, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee
      - 1984-1986 (Box 1)
      - Report, 1985 (Box 1)
- Budget/ Financial, 1980-1987
  The Budget/ Financial (1980-1987) series contains reports and correspondence related to departmental financial planning and gift donations.
  - Budget and Planning, 1980-1987; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Gifts and Donations, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
- Department Review and Reports, 1920-1996
  The Department Reviews and Reports (1920-1996) contains material that reviews or reports on the activities of the department. It is organized in three sub-series: Annual Reports, Department Organization, and Department Reviews. The Annual Reports sub-series contains the department’s annual reports from 1920 to 1996. The Department Organization sub-series contains documents that review the department’s organization and examine the merger with the Department of Computer and Communication Science. The Department Reviews sub-series contains internal reviews of the department from 1973 to 1996 and includes information which documents the review process, such as correspondence and surveys.
  - Annual Reports, 1920-1996
    - 1920-1949 (Box 1)
    - 1950-1968 (Box 1)
    - 1969-1979 (Box 1)
    - 1979-1987 (Box 1)
    - State of the EECS Department Report, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Department Organization, 1974-1987
    - Department Organization, 1974-1987; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - ECE-CCS Merger/ Reorganization, 1983-1987; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Department Review, 1973-1996
    - 1973 (Box 2)
    - Department Surveys, 1979-1986 (Box 2)
    - 1980, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1985 (Box 2)
    - 1986 (Box 2)
    - Research/ Department Review, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - Review Planning, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence re Review, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Departmental Review Committee, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Review Report, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Faculty Surveys, 1996 (Box 2)
- Histories, 1988-1995
  The Histories (1988-1995) series contains several histories written about the department, and some photocopied documents related to the history of the department, which were apparently collected in 1995 as part of a departmental centennial commemoration.
  - Histories of EECS Department, 1988-1995 (Box 2)
- Topical, 1977-1988
  The Topical (1965-1988) series contains files kept by the department on a range of topics, and is arranged alphabetically. Topics include admissions, alumni, honors and awards, Merit Computer Network/ ARPAnet, and military research.
  - Admissions
    - Policy, 1977-1983 (Box 2)
    - Statistics, 1988 (Box 2)
    - Undergraduate, 1984-1985 (Box 2)
  - Alumni Report, 1977-1982 (Box 2)
  - American Association of University Professors, 1972 (Box 2)
  - American Electronics Association-Hewlett Packard; Faculty Development, 1982-1983 (Box 2)
  - 75th Anniversary of Department, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Attwood Memorial Fund, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Bioengineering Program, 1979-1985 (Box 2)
  - Computing Fund Allocation, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Computer Needs Report, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - Counseling, Classification, Program Advisors, 1983-1987 (Box 2)
  - Cognitive Science Program, 1984-1985 (Box 2)
  - College Standing Committee, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Computer, Information, and Control Engineering Report
    - 1979-1982 (Box 3)
    - 1983 (Box 3)
  - Computer and Communication Science-Review, 1971-1980 (Box 3)
  - Course Offerings, 1984-1985 (Box 3)
  - Credit Examination, 1974-1975 (Box 3)
  - Department Computer Services Organization, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Department Seminar Series, 1984-1985 (Box 3)
  - Dow Distinguished Professorship, 1964-1975 (Box 3)
  - EECS Building Plans, 1986 (Box 3)
  - EECS Brochure, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Engineering Industrial Support Program, 1984-1988 (Box 3)
  - Equipment Requests, 1984-1985 (Box 3)
  - Equipment-MBE System, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
  - Faculty Activity Reports, 1983-1988 (Box 3)
  - Faculty Requests, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Graduate Program, 1984-1986; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Growth of Engineering Department, 1964-1969 (Box 3)
  - Honors and Awards
    - 1977-1984 (Box 3)
    - David Wise, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Humanities Department, 1981-1987 (Box 3)
  - Insight Management Seminar, 1987 (Box 3)
  - 1981 (Box 3)
  - Quest for Technology Program, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Industrial Technology Institute, 1982 (Box 3)
  - North Campus Building Plans, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - Microwave Science, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Research Corporation, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Joint Programs, 1981-1984 (Box 3)
  - Marwil Case, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Military Research, 1983-1984; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Robotics, 1982-1985 (Box 4)
  - Solid-State Electronics, 1985 (Box 4)
  - Statement on Faculty Salaries and Annual Merit Increases, 1982 (Box 4)
  - Student Grades Policy, 1977-1981 (Box 4)
  - Systems Engineering Lab, 1982 (Box 4)
  - University Procedures that Affect EECS, 1983-1987 (Box 4)
  - Wagner Professorship in Electrical Engineering, 1969-1975 (Box 4)
- Photographs, 1920-1985
  The Photographs (1920-1970) series contains photos of faculty, classes, equipment, and alumni gatherings. (Additional photographic material may be found in the separate record group: University of Michigan. Engineering Communications).
  - Individuals, circa 1945-1975 (Box 4)
  - Chrysler Center of Continuing Education, 1965 (Box 4)
  - Groups, Classes, Informal, circa 1920-1970 (Box 4)
  - Groups, Classes, Formal, circa 1930-1945 (Box 4)
  - Equipment, Laboratories, Classrooms, circa 1930-1985; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Buildings, circa 1935-1965 (Box 4)
  - Career Leaflet Pictures, circa 1963 (Box 4)
  - Research Review, 1967 (Box 4)
  - 75th Anniversary, 1970 (Box 4)
- Personnel
  The Personnel series contains records documenting the department’s hiring and promotion practices. The first subseries consists of alphabetically arranged files on faculty and research scientists. The records span from 1921 to 1997. Material includes documentation relating to hiring, summaries of research and teaching activities, resumés and biographical forms, sabbatical reports, and other pertinent correspondence. Some of the files also contain casebooks assembled during promotion or tenure reviews. The Memos and Correspondence subseries contains communication related to promotion and tenure decisions arranged chronologically from 1980 to 1991.
  - Faculty Files
    - Abraham, Santosh, 1987-1993 (Box 5)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2023 ]
    - Attwood, Steven S., 1929-1965 (Box 5)
    - Bado, Philippe, 1988-1992 (Box 5)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2022 ]
    - Bailey, Benjamin Franklin, 1921-1954 (Box 5)
    - Barak, Amnon, 1984-1988 (Box 5)
    - Baru, Chaitanya, 1987-1992 (Box 5)
    - Birdsall, Theodore, 1954-1996 (Box 5)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2026 ]
    - Biss, Ken, 1971-1978 (Box 5)
    - Black, James Richie, 1947-1961 (Box 5)
    - Blakely, Peter A., 1978-1983 (Box 5)
    - Boyd, Joseph A., 1949-1963 (Box 5)
    - Brietenback, Jerome R., 1983-1986 (Box 5)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2016 ]
    - Brown, April S., 1985-1986 (Box 5)
    - Brown, Richard B., 1987 (Box 5)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2017 ]
    - Brown, Richard K., 1940-1987; 1991 (Box 5)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1,] 2021 ]
    - Brown, William B., 1958-1988 (Box 5)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2018 ]
    - Bull, Hemstead Stratton, 1939-1967; 1984 (Box 5)
    - Butler, Thomas W., 1961-1984 (Box 5)
    - Cannon, Joseph H., 1921-1963 (Box 5)
    - Carey, Jack J., 1946-1973 (Box 5)
    - Chen, Kan, 1971-1996 (Box 5)
    - Chen, Yaochung, 1992-1994 (Box 5)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2024 ]
    - Chu, Chiao-Min, 1947-1989 (Box 5)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2019 ]
    - Cicerone, Ralph, 1969-1977 (Box 5)
    - Compton, Kevin J., 1990 (Box 5)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2020 ]
    - Crary, Selden B., 1994 (Box 5)
    - Cravens, Thomas E., 1980 (Box 5)
    - Curtice, Walter R., 1967-1972 (Box 5)
    - Cutrona, Louis J., 1950-1971 (Box 5)
    - Daws, James L., Jr., 1965-1997 (Box 5)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2027 ]
    - Delp, Edward, 1979-1984 (Box 5)
    - Diamond, Howard, 1958-1972 (Box 5)
    - Drummond, Timothy J., 1987-1989 (Box 5)
    - East, Jack, 1982 (Box 5)
    - Ebbini, Emad, 1989-1998 (Box 5)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2028 ]
    - Enns, Mark W., 1968-1988 (Box 6)
    - Feak, Glen A. B., 1988-1991 (Box 6)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2021 ]
    - Finerman, Aaron, 1979-1994 (Box 6)
    - Franklin, Robert L., 1987-1988 (Box 6)
    - Freudenberg, James, 1990 (Box 6)
    - Frieder, Gideon, 1981-1989 (Box 6)
    - Galiana, Francisco, 1974-1976 (Box 6)
    - Ganapathy, Kicha, 1976-1982; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Garner, Harvey, 1955-1970 (Box 6)
    - Gault, James S., 1925-1951 (Box 6)
    - Gelenbe, Erol, 1969-1980 (Box 6)
    - Giles, Martin, 1989-1994 (Box 6)
    - Gomberg, Henry J., 1940-1961 (Box 6)
    - Grimes, Dale M., 1951-1977 (Box 6)
    - Grizzle, Jessy W., 1990 (Box 6)
    - Haddock, Fred T., 1955-1967 (Box 6)
    - Haddock, Thomas, 1985-1990 (Box 6)
    - Hadj-Alouane, Atidel, 1994-1997 (Box 6)
    - Hall, Cordelia, 1987-1990 (Box 6)
    - Hansell, Gregory L., 1982-1984 (Box 6)
    - Haralick, Robert M., 1985-1987 (Box 6)
    - Harger, Robert, 1963-1965 (Box 6)
    - Hellwarth, Arlen, 1953-1980 (Box 6)
    - Hendrick, Walter, 1947-1992 (Box 6)
    - Hero, Alfred O, III, 1989-1990 (Box 6)
    - Hiatt, Ralph E., 1958-1980 (Box 6)
    - Higbie, Henry Harold, 1947 (Box 6)
    - Hok, Gunnar, 1945-1976 (Box 6)
    - Holland, Lewis N., 1925-1982 (Box 6)
    - Hsieh, Hsung-Chen, 1964-1968 (Box 6)
    - Jackson, Phil, 1977-1978 (Box 6)
    - Jain, Ramesh C., 1981-1994 (Box 6)
    - Jenkins, Janice M, 1983-1989; 2 folders
      - Folder 1 (Box 6)
      - Folder 2 (Box 7)
    - Jha, Niraj Kumar, 1984-1987 (Box 7)
    - Jin, Jiaming, 1989-1992 (Box 7)
    - Kahn, Peter, 1965-1979 (Box 7)
    - Kamash, Kishore, 1994-1998 (Box 7)
    - Katehi, Pisti, 1988 (Box 7)
    - Kazda, Louis F., 1946-1984 (Box 7)
    - Kerr, William, 1948-1965 (Box 7)
    - Knoblock, Todd A., 1987-1992 (Box 7)
    - Kortesoja, Alan, 1986-1989 (Box 7)
    - Krieger, Frank J., 1982 (Box 7)
    - Kuga, Yasuo, 1988-1991 (Box 7)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2091 ]
    - LaFortune, Stephane, 1988 (Box 7)
    - LaFrieda, James R., 1972-1974 (Box 7)
    - Laird, John E., 1988 (Box 7)
    - Lawler, Eugene L., 1961-1970 (Box 7)
    - Lawrence, William N., 1958-1968 (Box 7)
    - Lee, C. S. George, 1979-1985 (Box 7)
    - Lee, Yung-Chia, 1984-1990 (Box 7)
    - Lenfant, Jacques, 1975 (Box 7)
    - Li, Weiqui, 1989-1995 (Box 7)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2025 ]
    - Liepa, Valdis V., 1976 (Box 7)
    - Liu, Xinbing, 1994-1997 (Box 7)
    - Lovell, Alfred H., 1921-1960; 1974 (Box 7)
    - Lyon, John A. M., 1950-1997 (Box 7)
    - Lytinen, Steven, 1986-1994 (Box 7)
    - McAfee, Leo C., 1976-1977 (Box 7)
    - McCleer, 1982-1985 (Box 7)
    - McInnes, Peter, 1972-1973 (Box 7)
    - McMahon, E. Lawrence, 1959-1994 (Box 7)
    - McMullen, Charles W., 1960-1986; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Macnee, Bruce, 1950-1989; 1999 (Box 7)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2029 ]
    - Mains, Richard, 1989 (Box 8)
    - Majewski, Marian L., 1982-1985 (Box 8)
    - Martin, Edward A., 1951-1986 (Box 8)
    - Martin, Edwin R., 1947-1971 (Box 8)
    - Masnari, Nino A., 1964-1979 (Box 8)
    - Mattes, Benton L., 1977-1983 (Box 8)
    - Mazumder, Pinaki, 1990 (Box 8)
    - Metzger, Kurt, 1987-1994 (Box 8)
    - Miller, Murray H., 1951-1971 (Box 8)
    - Mishra, Umesh K., 1985-1986 (Box 8)
    - Moore, Arthur D., 1947-1989; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Mouzon, James C., 1957-1975 (Box 8)
    - Mudge, Trevor, 1989-1990 (Box 8)
    - Nadel, Bernard, 1983-1986 (Box 8)
    - Nagpal, Krishnan, 1989-1996 (Box 8)
    - Narasimhamurthi, Natarajan, 1980-1987 (Box 8)
    - Naylor, Arch, 1959-1993 (Box 8)
    - Nelson, Thomas, 1968-1974 (Box 8)
    - Neuhoff, David L., 1980; 1984 (Box 8)
    - Ng, Geok, 1990-1993 (Box 8)
    - Nourani, Farshid, 1979-1980 (Box 8)
    - Nozari, Fahed, 1977-1978 (Box 8)
    - Nudel, Bernard (Box 8)
      (see: Nadel, Bernard)
    - Olte, Andrejs, 1958-1985 (Box 8)
    - Owings, Clyde L., 1978 (Box 8)
    - Park, Jaehong, 1991-1994 (Box 8)
    - Pavlidis, Dimitris, 1988 (Box 8)
    - Pennington, Anthony J., 1959-1968 (Box 9)
    - Peterson, Dean, 1976-1981 (Box 9)
    - Peterson, Gordon E., 1958-1967 (Box 9)
    - Phillips, Richard, 1984-1987 (Box 9)
    - Plban, Uwe, 1980-1988 (Box 9)
    - Porcello, Leonard, 1958-1975 (Box 9)
    - Porter, William A., 1960-1979 (Box 9)
    - Prohaska, Otto, 1983-1985 (Box 9)
    - Quek, Francis Kok How, 1989-1993 (Box 9)
    - Rajlich, Vaclav, 1981-1985 (Box 9)
    - Raney, Russell K., 1971-1976 (Box 9)
    - Rauch, Lawrence L., 1971-1979 (Box 9)
    - Ravishankar, Chinya, 1988 (Box 9)
    - Reddy, Umapathi, 1986-1993 (Box 9)
    - Ribbens, William B., 1977; 1981 (Box 9)
    - Rizzoni, Giorgio, 1988-1990 (Box 9)
    - Robinson, Andrew L., 1984-1993 (Box 9)
    - Samir, Uri., 1969-1971 (Box 9)
    - Sayler, John H., 1987-1989 (Box 9)
    - Schunck, Brian G., 1985-1992 (Box 9)
    - Scott, Norman R., 1945-1988 (Box 9)
    - Scott, Paul, 1980-1986 (Box 9)
    - Shabe, Sunil, 1968-1973 (Box 9)
    - Shapiro, Linda, 1985-1986 (Box 9)
    - Sharpe, Charles B., 1952-1988 (Box 9)
    - Sherlekar, Deepak, 1987-1991 (Box 9)
    - Shin, Kang G., 1984-1985 (Box 9)
    - Siegel, Keeve M., 1956-1975 (Box 9)
    - Smith, Douglas, 1981-1987 (Box 9)
    - Smith, Newbern, 1954-1971; 1988 (Box 9)
    - Steel, Duncan, 1988 (Box 9)
    - Sternberg, Stanley, 1979-1983 (Box 9)
    - Stout, Melville B., 1937-1965; 1994 (Box 9)
    - Strauss, Jon C., 1970-1971 (Box 9)
    - Stroke, George W., 1962-1967; 3 folders (Box 10)
    - Tacer, M. Emin, 1978-1980 (Box 10)
    - Tarboux, Joseph G., 1952-1959 (Box 10)
    - Teneketzis, Demosthenis, 1988 (Box 10)
    - Teory, Toby J., 1978 (Box 10)
    - Thatte, Satish, 1983-1988 (Box 10)
    - Thomas, Spencer, 1990 (Box 10)
    - Tsui, Louis, 1984 (Box 10)
    - Underwood, Steven E., 1994 (Box 10)
    - Valdmanis, Janis A., 1988-1994 (Box 10)
    - Volakis, John, 1988 (Box 10)
    - Volz, Richard A., 1964-1989; 2 folders (Box 10)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2019 ]
    - Wakefield, Gregeory H., 1988 (Box 10)
    - Walker, Michael W., 1985-1992 (Box 10)
    - Weinberger, Doreen L., 1983-1991 (Box 10)
    - Welch, H. William, 1946-1957 (Box 10)
    - Weymouth, Terry E., 1987 (Box 10)
    - Williamson, Steven L., 1988-1994 (Box 10)
    - Yu, Francis, 1975-1977 (Box 10)
    - Zatkalik, Jovan, 1973-1974 (Box 10)
  - Memos and Correspondence regarding Faculty Promotion and Tenure
    - 1982-1991, 7 folders (Box 10)